Guide to the John B. Oakes Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series IV: Writings
  - Subseries IV.4: Foreign Travel and Related Article
    - Taiwan, 1980 (Box 91)
    - Trip to Philippines, 1980 (Box 91)
    - China, 1980 (Box 91)
    - Alaska, 1980-1984 (Box 91)
    - Romania, 1982 (Box 91)
    - Trip to Balkans-Yugoslavia, 4/86 (Box 91)
    - Trip to the Balkans—Romania, 4/82 (Box 92)
    - Trip to Yugoslavia (Box 92)
    - Trip to Romania, April-May 1982 (Box 92)
    - Trip to Bulgaria, April 1982 (Box 92)
    - Trip to Morocco, February 1984 (Box 92)
    - Tunisia, 1984 (Box 92)
    - Trip to Tunisia, March 1984 (Box 92)
    - Trip to Honduras, October 1984 (Box 92)
    - Trip to El Salvador, October 1984 (Box 92)
    - Trip to Nicaragua, October 1984 (Box 92)
    - Nicaragua, 1984/86 (Box 92)
    - El Salvador, 1984/1989 (Box 92)
    - Trip to Alaska, August-September 1985 (Box 92)
    - Trip to Cuba, October 1985 (Box 92)
    - Cuba, 1985 (Box 92)
    - Trip to London and Paris, April 1986 (Box 92)
    - China, 1986 (Box 92)
  - Subseries IV.5: Book Reviews and Opinon
    - Book Reviews by JBO, 1950-1957 (Box 93)
    - Book Review of “Masters of Deceit”, 1958 (Box 93)
    - Campomenosi (Box 93)
    - “Edge of Freedom” Publishers (Box 93)
    - “Edge of Freedom” Reviews and Congratulations (Box 93)
    - Freedom of the Press (Box 93)
    - JFK/Lindsay Edits by JBO (Box 93)
    - Kennedy, Robert F., 1968-9 (Box 93)
    - Letters from Russia (reprinted in the Washington Post Feb.1938) (Box 93)
    - Letters to the Editor JBO (Box 93)
    - Letters to Prospective Journalists (Box 93)
    - NY Times Magazine Articles (Box 93)
    - Press-Managing the News (Box 93)
    - Testimony-Congress 1988 Freedom of the Press in South Africa (Box 93)
    - “The Trust” (Box 93)
  - Subseries IV.6: Rhodes Sscholar Essays
    - Unsorted Essays (7) (Box 94)
  - Subseries IV.7: Interviews/Research For Writings
    - CA Environment (Box 95)
    - Conservation (Box 95)
    - Conservation: Bering Strait Preserve (Box 95)
    - Conservation: Martha’s Vineyard (Box 95)
    - Conservation: Martha’s Vineyard, 1972-1973 (Box 95)
    - Conservation Organization (Box 95)
    - Interview with Milovan Djilas, (appeared 6/20/82) (Box 95)
    - Interview with John F. Kennedy (Box 95)
    - Interview with John V. Lindsay (Box 95)
    - Interview with Lyndon B. Johnson (Box 95)
    - Interview with Nelson Rockefeller (Box 95)
    - Op-Ed General (Box 95)
    - Proposed Op-Ed Pieces (some by notables) (Box 96)
- Series V: Speeches and Memorials
  - Series V.1: Subjects
    - Adirondack Council (Box 97)
    - Collegiate (Box 97)
    - New York City (Box 97)
    - The Press (Box 97)
    - Princeton Graduation and Valedictory, 1934 (Box 97)
    - Speeches 1 (Box 97)
  - Series V.2: Chronological
    - 1949-1969 (Box 98)
    - Kent School, 1949 (Box 98)
    - Teachers’ In-Service Course—Speech on Community, March 1953 (Box 98)
    - Teachers’ In-Service Course—Speech on Communism WDR-TV Prog. ”America Speaks”, 10/31/53 (Box 98)
    - Issues and Politics Speech Phi Beta Kappa Society, 1954 (Box 98)
    - NY Womens Adv’t Club Speech on the Printed Word, Feb. 1954 (Box 98)
    - Teachers’ In-Service Course in Reinforcing Amer. Freedom, April 1955 (Box 98)
    - Connecticut College Speech on Women, June 1955 (Box 98)
    - Chattanooga University, 10/20/1955 (Box 98)
    - “Should the State Dept. Allow Reporters to Go to Red China?”, Recorded March 1957 (Box 98)
    - WQXR Youth Forum, 1958 (Box 98)
    - Mount Holyoke College Conference “The Right of the People to Know”, May 1958 (Box 98)
    - The Open Mind “The Individual and U.S. Foreign Policy, 11/16/58 (Box 98)
    - University of Hartford Speech Commencement, June 1960 (Box 98)
    - WBAI-FM “The Jet-Propelled Bulldozer Speech, July 1960 (Box 98)
    - The New Role of Neutralism Speech Cos Club, Nov. 1960 (Box 98)
    - University of Hartford: Intro of Harve Alphand, “France and World Affairs”, 11/29/60 (Box 98)
    - Columbia-Catherwood Speeches on Franco-American Relations, 1/10/61 3/61 (Box 98)
    - Marquette University Speeches, March 1962 (Box 98)
    - Collegiate School Speeches, 1963 (Box 98)
    - Princeton University—Speech, February 1963 (Box 98)
    - Bryn Mawr Speeches, February 1963 (Box 98)
    - Montana State University—Speech, May 1963 (Box 98)
    - Oxford School (Hartford) Speech, 1963 (Box 98)
    - Pomona College-Speech Commencement, June 1963 (Box 98)
    - Dartmouth College: Speech, March 1964 (Box 98)
    - Stanford Forum on World Affairs Speech, April 1967 (Box 98)
    - Rhodes Scholar Reunion—Speech, June 1965 (Box 98)
    - University of California Speeches-Press-Enterprise, 5/8/1967 (Box 98)
    - Meet the Press—JBO, August 25 1968 (Box 98)
    - Lindbergh Introduction (Box 98)
    - Jefferson Award—Speech, February 1968 (Box 98)
    - Nassau Club Speech Princeton NJ, May 1968 (Box 98)
    - Garden Club of America Award Speech, April 1969 (Box 98)
    - Chatham College—Speeches Commencement, May 1969 (Box 98)
    - Woodrow Wilson School of Public and International Affairs (Box 98)
    - 1970-1978 (Box 99)
    - American Society of Newspaper Editors A.S.N.E, May 1970 (Box 99)
    - American Newspaper Publisher Association, April 22, 1970 (Box 99)
    - Princeton University Speech, June 1970 (Box 99)
    - The Bryant Library Lectures: An Editor’s Perspective, Roslyn, Long Island, 5/11/71 (Box 99)
    - Speech—Century Assn., 6/3/71 (Box 99)
    - Meet the Press, 1/9/72 (Box 99)
    - Dedication Speech at Portland State University, Nov 30, 1972 (Box 99)
      [NB: Includes material re: contretemps with The Oregonian]
    - Architectural League of NY, 12/73 (Box 99)
    - Introduction of Katherine Graham at Cosmopolitan Cub, 12/12/73 (Box 99)
    - Speech at Univ. of Oregon Credibility of the Press, 2/14/75 (Box 99)
    - Speech at Dickinson College, Carlisle, PA, 2/23/75 (Box 99)
    - Speech—Princetonian Banquet, 4/75 (Box 99)
    - Speech for Union of American Hebrew Congregations (Box 99)
    - Speech for 10th Anniversary of White House Fellows, May 30, 1975 (Box 99)
    - GWO Memorial, Whig Hall Princeton, 9/27/75 (Box 99)
    - Temple Emanu-El Speech, 11/75 (Box 99)
      [The USA 200 Years Later]
    - Speech—Hebrew Union College, 2/76 (Box 99)
    - The Responsibilities of the Press (Box 99)
    - Tribute to Mrs. A.H. Sulzberger (Box 99)
    - The Parks Council, 6/76 (Box 99)
    - NRDC Award to Barbara Ward presented by JBO, 10/20/76 (Box 99)
    - Audubon Medal Award Speech, 1976 (Box 99)
    - Notes Introducing Lindsay at National Council of Editorial Writers (Box 99)
    - Editorial Writers (Box 99)
    - Deadline Club Award (Box 99)
    - NRDC Award Luncheon, Harvard Club, Oct. 18 1977 (Box 99)
    - JBO Speech at Cosmopolitan Club, 10/26/77 (Box 99)
    - Speech Ode to MacIntyre, 1/28/78 (Box 99)
    - Syracuse Press Club, February 5, 1978 (Box 99)
    - Salzburg Seminar on Mass Media, March 5-23 1978 (Box 99)
    - “Soft Energy Paths” CFR Meeting in Honor of Amory Lovins, 3/5/79 (Box 100)
    - JBO Collegiate Speech, 6/6/1979 (Box 100)
    - Press Freedom vs. Press Responsibility, Princeton U., 6/8/79 (Box 100)
    - Meet the Press, July 8, 1979 (Box 100)
    - American Press Institute Speech Material, 1-8-80 (Box 100)
    - Binghamton-Harpur Forum, The FDN of the State University of New York (Box 100)
    - Center for Communication. Population Resource Center, 11/18/80 (Box 100)
    - Princeton Speech, May 6, 1981 (Box 100)
    - Transcript/Acknowledgments: “Firing Line,”, Harvard U., 1/7/82 (Box 100)
    - Silurians Players Club, NY, 1/18/82 (Box 100)
    - Speech C.A.N. Consumer Action Now, May 25, 1982 (Box 100)
    - Speech, Bryn Mawr, 4/13-14/83 (Box 100)
    - Florida Southern College Speech, 11/9/83 (Box 100)
    - Yale University (Liberal Party), 12/5/83 (Box 100)
    - Power and Politics M.V., 7/26/1984 (Box 100)
    - Tribute to Jean Picker (Mrs. Harvey Picker) (Box 100)
    - Speech CUNY: Lawlessness in Central America, 3/6/85 (Box 100)
    - Speech: Lawlessness in Central America: CUNY: Ralph Bunche Inst., 3/6/85 (Box 100)
    - Speech—Funders Conference Re: Central America Samuel Rubin Foundation, 3/14/85 (Box 100)
    - Speech U.S. Policy in Latin America in Funders Conference, New York, 3/14/85 (Box 100)
    - Speech, Gannet Center for Media Studies (Box 100)
    - Graham Hovey, University of Michigan, May 10, 1986 (Box 100)
    - N.Y. Parks and Coms Assn. Dinner, 6/12/91 (Box 100)
    - Lawrenceville Medal, 10/94 (Box 100)
    - Temple Emanu-El, 11/94 (Box 100)
    - Aronson, 4/19/96 (Box 100)
    - Bendiener—Oral History (Box 100)
    - Speech Notes (Box 100)
    - Cary, William L., 2/10/83 and 11/4/83 (Box 101)
    - Fischer, John, 9/21/78 (Box 101)
    - Hough Memorial, Aug. 1985 (Box 101)
    - Lang, Daniel, November 20, 1981 (Box 101)
    - Lash, Joseph P., 10/5/87 (Box 101)
    - McKeever, Porter, 4/21/92 11/7/65 (Box 101)
    - Merz, Charles, 1/9/78 (Box 101)
    - Nathan, Adele Gutman, 7/31/86 (Box 101)
    - Raskin, Abraham (Box 101)
    - Reston APS Memorial, 1998 (Box 101)
    - Salisbury APS Memorial (Box 101)
    - Sellon, Perry (Box 101)
    - Shannon, William V. (Box 101)
    - Silk (Box 101)
    - Werner, Walter, 12/14/86 and 1/20/87 (Box 101)
  - Subseries V.3: Memorials and Obituaries
    - Temple Emanu-el Memorial Service for John B. Oakes, New York City, 9 April 2001, (2 page photocopy ) (Box 101)
    - Temple Emanu-el Memorial Service for John B. Oakes: Tributes by John H. Adams; Herbert Mitgang; Andra N. Oakes; Alison H. Oakes & Cynthia J. Oakes; John G.H. Oakes, New York City, 9 April 2001, (14 page volume ) (Box 101)
    - Obituaries from: The Boston Globe; Chicago Tribune; The Collegiate Review; The New York Times; Time; U.S. News & World Report; Vineyard Gazette; The Washington Post, 2001 (Box 101)
    - Memorials from: American Oxonian; American Philosophical Society; The Collegiate Review; Lawrentian, 2001 (Box 101)
- Series VI: Printed Material
  - Subseries VI.1: Magazines
    - American Oxonian, Oct. 1943-Spring 2001 (gaps) (Box 102)
  - Subseries VI.2: Unsorted Clippings
    - Biographical Clippings/Souvenirs (unsorted); Press Memorabilia, Political Memorabilia, JBO Articles for Chin Strap (Box 103)
    - Clippings: Obituaries/Biographies (Box 104)
    - Clippings: New York Times/Washington Post (unsorted) (Box 105)
    - Clippings: New York Times/Trenton State Gazette/Washington Post (Box 106)
    - Clippings: New York Times/Saturday Evening Post/Washington Post (Box 107)
    - Clippings: Environmental (Box 108)
  - Subseries VI.3: Books and Magazines
    - Congressional Record (Box 109)
    - Democratic Convention, 1964 (Box 109)
    - Famous Editorials (Box 109)
    - Harpers “The New York Times Part II” Guy Talese (Box 109)
    - The John F. Kennedys: A Family Album Mark Shaw (Box 109)
    - Life: Picasso (Box 109)
    - Litigation Implications of the U.S. Withdrawal from the Nicaragua Case (Box 109)
    - Magazine Clippings of JBO (Box 109)
    - Media Freedom and Accountability (Box 109)
    - New York Magazine “Who Runs the City” Edward Costikyan (Box 109)
    - Princeton University Alumni (Box 109)
    - Woodrow Wilson School of Public and International Affairs (Box 109)
  - Subseries VI.4: Writings Of Others
    - Thaddeus Holt Chapters 13/15 of A History of Strategic Deception (Box 110)
    - Louis Campomenosi NY Times Editorial Policy on Vietnam, 1945-1965 (Box 111)
- Series VII: Scrapbooks
  - Subseries VII.1: Regular Size
    - Columbia-Catherwood Award, 1961 (Box 112)
    - Edge of Freedom Reviews (Box 112)
  - Subseries VII.2: Oversize Scrapbooks
    - Editorials, May 18, 1949-April 16, 1953 (Box 670)
    - Conservation, Dec. 3, 1950-5/18/61 (Box 671)
    - Editorials, 2/26/53-8/23/56 (Box 672)
    - Book Reviews and Articles, Sept. 1950-Nov. 1959 (Box 673)
    - Editorials August 23, 1956-January 21, 1958 (Box 673)
    - August 24, 1956-January 21, 1958 (Box Flat Box674)
    - Scrapbook, [1960-1961] (Box 674)
    - Editorials, Jan. 1950-Jan. 1961 (Box 675)
    - Editorials, Jan. 1961-Jan. 1962 (Box 675)
    - Editorials, 1963-[Nov 1, 1964] (Box 676)
    - John B. Oakes, April 23, 1963 (Box 676)
    - Editorials and Articles, January 1967 to 12/31/76 (Box 677)
    - Personal Scrapbook, January 1967-[1978] (Box 677)
    - Articles Written by John B. Oakes, 1977-1979 (Box 678)
    - Articles Written by John B. Oakes, 1980-84 (Box 678)
    - Articles Written by John B. Oakes, 1985…[1991] (Box 679)
- Series VIII: Related Material
  - Subseries VIII.1: Oakes Material In Other Archives
    - New York Times (Box 113)
    - Wisconsin Historical Society (Box 113)